Inventory of Wills from District Court (Third District: Salt Lake County), 1869-
Utah State Archives and Records Service
District Court (Third District: Salt Lake County) Wills
1869-
Utah State Archives and Records Service 300 South Rio Grande Salt Lake City, UT 84101-1182 801-533-3535 historyresearch@utah.gov
Series 3578
District Court (Third District: Salt Lake County)
43 microfilm reels
Legislators at the second Utah Territorial Legislative Assembly organized probate courts in each of Utah's counties and endowed these courts with the right to exercise jurisdiction in the probate of wills and the administration of estates of deceased persons. By law any person of full age and of sound mind could dispose of all of his property by will, with the exception that sufficient first be withheld to pay any outstanding debts. The signatures of two competent witnesses in addition to the testator validated a completed will. The law provided that wills could be sealed and deposited with the clerk of the probate court where they would be preserved until the death of the testator.
Historical Note
An agency history is available.
Legislators at the second Utah Territorial Legislative Assembly organized probate courts in each of Utah's counties and endowed these courts with the right to exercise jurisdiction in the probate of wills and the administration of estates of deceased persons (Laws of Utah, Chapter 42, 1852). The assembly clarified the manner in which estates should be settled. By law any person of full age and of sound mind could dispose of all of his property by will, with the exception that sufficient first be withheld to pay any outstanding debts. The signatures of two competent witnesses in addition to the testator validated a completed will. The law provided that wills could be sealed and deposited with the clerk of the probate court where they would be preserved until the death of the testator. Otherwise, any person having custody of a will could bring it into the court at the death of the testator. The law stated that if the court allowed and attested the will, it should be carried into effect (Compiled Laws of Utah, 1876, Title 14, chapter 1, sections 1-6).
Each will follows a similar format. It states that the testator meets the requirement of being of sound mind and legal age. It names who the testator desires to be the executor of his estate. It enumerates the testator's property and designates whom he wishes to inherit each item.
Research Note
Many persons died intestate, or without leaving a will. These cases are not represented in this series. Early wills in this series were originally part of probate case files (series 1621). However, at some point the court began separating wills from the probate case files. Someone subsequently went through the case files to remove previously filed wills and file them separately. In 1978 the two files were microfilmed separately. In 2002-2003 the first 922 cases were microfilmed a second time and with this filming all wills were returned to the appropriate case files before filming. Some early wills appear both in this series and in the relevant case file (series 1621). If wills were overlooked in the process of retrieving them for the files, they remain with the remainder of the case as originally filed. Some reels contain retakes of cases that were microfilmed unsatisfactorily or were missing at the time of filming. Retakes are spliced at the ends of reels, so if a case does not appear in sequence, check for retakes at the end of the reel. Retakes for cases filed 1964-1969 are at the beginning of the reel. All probate case files and associated wills filed since 1 January 1970 remain in the custody of Third District Court: Salt Lake County. All probate case files and associated wills filed since 1 January 1970 remain in the custody of Third District Court: Salt Lake County.
Numerical by case number.
This series is classified as Public.
The Salt Lake County Probate Court initially had jurisdiction in the probate of estates and began keeping and numbering probate case files. At statehood, county probate courts were abolished and jurisdiction for the probate of estates in Salt Lake County passed to Third District Court: Salt Lake County.
These records were acquired from the creating agency through established retention schedules.
Indexes: An on-line electronic index has been created for probate cases filed 1852-1897. View index.
Probate case files from the District Court (Third District: Salt Lake County), Series 1621, are the complete case files which correspond to the wills in this series.
Estate registers from the District Court (Third District: Salt Lake County), Series 3927, provide a list of all actions taken in each case. Registers can be consulted to determine whether or not a will was included in a particular probate case.
Probate records index from the District Court (Third District: Salt Lake County), Series 17611, provides reference to Third District Court probate case files, and indirectly to the wills in this series.
Politics, Government, and Law; Civil Procedure and Courts
Wills--Utah--Salt Lake County.; Inheritance and succession--Utah--Salt Lake County.; Probate courts--Utah--Salt Lake County.
- Wills, 1869-; 43 microfilm reels
  - 147 - 911 (Reel 1, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 930 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 936 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 938 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 942 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 943 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 945 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 948 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 952 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 961 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 970 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1011 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1026 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1027 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1030 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1083 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1084 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1091 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1120 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1121 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1128 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1155 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1157 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1168 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1169 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1174 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1191 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1192 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1128 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1202 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1215 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1222 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1226 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1258 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 1271 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 1283 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 1314 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 1216 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 1338 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 1339 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 1340 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 1353 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 1355 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 1358 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 1363 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 1377 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 45)
  - 1379 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 46)
  - 1392 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 47)
  - 1403 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 48)
  - 1418 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 49)
  - 1423 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 50)
  - 1447 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 51)
  - 1450 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 52)
  - 1486 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 53)
  - 1489 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 54)
  - 1496 (microfilmed as 1469) (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 55)
  - 1517 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 56)
  - 1520 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 57)
  - 1526 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 58)
  - 1591 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 59)
  - 1639 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 60)
  - 1650 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 61)
  - 1659 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 62)
  - 1740 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 63)
  - 2175 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 64)
  - 1788 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 65)
  - 1846 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 66)
  - 1871 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 67)
  - 1882 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 68)
  - 1911 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 69)
  - 1932 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 70)
  - 1939 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 71)
  - 2118 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 72)
  - 2180 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 73)
  - 2187 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 74)
  - 2223 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 75)
  - 2244 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 76)
  - 2418 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 77)
  - 2466 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 78)
  - 2506 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 79)
  - 2561 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 80)
  - 2578 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 81)
  - 2611 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 82)
  - 2633 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 83)
  - 2670 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 84)
  - 2750 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 85)
  - 2938 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 86)
  - 2940 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 87)
  - 2965 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 88)
  - 3007 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 89)
  - 3042 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 90)
  - 3078 - 4043 (Reel 1, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 4056 - 4924 (Reel 2, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 4926 - 6080 (Reel 3, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 6081 - 7153 (Reel 4, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 7164 - 8384 (Reel 5, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 8400 - 9842 (Reel 6, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 9844 - 10987 (Reel 7, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 10990 - 12049 (Reel 8, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 12051 - 13354 (Reel 9, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 13369 - 14510 (Reel 10, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 14512 - 15652 (Reel 11, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 15666 - 16847 (Reel 12, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 16853 - 17927 (Reel 13, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 17940 - 19444 (Reel 14, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 19452 - 20865 (Reel 15, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 20868 - 22152 (Reel 16, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 22166 - 23371 (Reel 17, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 23373 - 24433 (Reel 18, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 24439 - 26122 (Reel 19, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 26123 - 28415 (Reel 20, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 28419 - 30673 (Reel 21, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 30680 - 32133 (Reel 22, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 32144 - 34131 (Reel 23, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 34133 - 35924 (Reel 24, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 35929 - 37534 (Reel 25, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 37586 - 38786 (Reel 26, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 38804 - 40265 (Reel 27, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 40266 - 41542 (Reel 28, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 41545 - 42596 (Reel 29, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 42600 - 43761 (Reel 30, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 43768 - 44996 (Reel 31, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 45008 - 46308 (Reel 32, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 46313 - 47535 (Reel 33, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 47537 - 48038 (Reel 34, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 48044 - 49400 (Reel 35, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 49403 - 50503 (Reel 36, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 50514 - 51541 (Reel 37, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 51545 - 52599 (Reel 38, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 52601 - 53503 (Reel 39, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 53507 - 54427 (Reel 40, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 54428 - 55422 (Reel 41, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 55430 - 56101 (Reel 42, Box N/A, Folder N/A)
  - 56111 - 56582 (Reel 43, Box N/A, Folder N/A)